We're continuing our discussion of how
spinners are used in particle physics.
In the previous video, we discussed the
theory behind the DRA equation,
including what the gamas mean, what
direct spinners are, and the concepts of
left and right kirality.
In the next few videos, I'm going to be
working up to the solutions of the DRA
equation.
to help us understand the solutions of
the direct equation better. In this
video, I'm going to solve the Klein
Gordon equation. Then in the next video,
I'll solve the ProAka equation.
The Klein Gordon equation describes a
scalar field and has wavelike solutions.
The ProAka equation describes a vector
field and it also has wavelike
solutions. But the vector nature of the
field allows waves with the same
frequencies to have different
polarizations
like horizontal, vertical, and
longitudinal polarizations.
Finally, the direct equation describes
spinner fields and also has wavelike
solutions, but the spinner nature of the
field allows waves with the same
frequencies to have either spin up or
spin down orientations.
We'll also see that the direct equation
has both matter and antimatter solutions
and this is related to the concepts of
left and right kirality.
We'll also talk about how kirality
relates to the helicity of a spinner
particle.
Each of these three equations will get
its own video explaining the solutions.
We'll start in this video with the Klein
Gordon equation solutions for scalar
fields.
Now all of the fields in this video are
going to be purely classical fields
which means we can know the exact field
values and field momenta together at the
same time. So the fields are not yet
quantized.
If you want to see how to use
commutators and anti-commutators to
quantize these classical fields to get
quantum fields, you can watch video 21
in this series.
So let's start with the Klein Gordon
equation which describes the behavior of
a relativistic scalar field fi. As a
review of video 21, a one-dimensional
scalar field is like a one-dimensional
collection of masses on springs all
connected with rubber bands.
X gives the location of a mass along the
X ais and PH of X gives the amplitude of
the mass located at position X.
The kinetic energy of a specific mass is
related to the square of the time
derivative of f ofx, which indicates how
fast the mass is shaking. Since we'll be
working with special relativity, we
always put a factor of the speed of
light c next to the time t to give units
of meters, which puts time on equal
footing with space coordinates.
The potential energy for a mass due to
the extension of its spring is related
to the square of the amplitude phi. So
how much the spring is extended as well
as the stiffness of the spring which is
denoted with a spring constant.
In field theory we commonly write this
spring constant as mass times the speed
of light C divided by the reduced planks
constant H bar.
So this is a mass term and we can think
of the field's mass as sort of like the
field's stiffness or how difficult it is
to excite the field. The factors of C
and H bar also help give this term
consistent units with all the other
terms in the equation which have units
of 1 over distance squared.
With purely classical fields, the factor
of h bar is often left out, but I'm
going to leave it in for these videos.
even if we are dealing with classical
fields that have not been quantized yet.
Finally, there is also potential energy
due to the rubber bands connecting the
masses. When two neighboring masses are
at different amplitudes, the rubber
bands will try and pull them back
together. So, this potential energy is
related to the square of the derivative
of phi with respect to x.
We say that these energies are really
energy densities because they give us
the energy per mass located at position
x.
Taking the kinetic and potential energy
densities, we can use their sum to get
the field's Hamiltonian density and use
their difference to get the field's
lrangeian density.
To get the equations of motion for the
field, we can put this Klein Gordon
Lrangeian through the Oiler Lrange
equation for fields.
To do this, I'm going to rewrite the
derivatives using subscript notation.
Now, with the field oiler lrange
equations, we treat the field phi and
its derivatives as independent
variables. So, taking the partial
derivative with respect to phi. All
terms go to zero except the last one
where power rule decreases the power by
one and brings a factor of two in front.
For taking the derivative with respect
to partial ctfi,
all terms go to zero except the first
one and power rule gives us partial ctfi
as a result.
Similarly, for the partial xfi
derivative, we get negative partial xfi
as a result.
Knowing all this, if we expand the sum
in the Oiler Lrange equation to include
the time and x indices and plug in the
derivative terms, when we bring
everything to one side, we get the Klein
Gordon equation. This is the equation of
motion for a scalar field phi that we
described with the Klein Gordon Lronian.
If we want to extend this to a
three-dimensional Klein Gordon field
that depends on X, Y, and Zed, we just
need to include gradient terms in the
potential energy density for the Y and Z
directions. And these get corresponding
terms in the Klein Gordon equation.
Now, if we pull out the fi field in
front, we can notice all these second
derivative terms in the four space-time
directions.
The time derivative has a plus sign in
front and the space derivatives all get
minus signs.
We can write this sum of four terms
using arrays with an inner row column
product. If we include this matrix in
the middle that have the correct signs
along the diagonal. This is the manovsky
metric ADA that you should recognize
from special relativity.
We can also write this array
multiplication using Einstein summation
notation where we have implied
summations over the mu and new indices
that range from 0 to 3. Here index 0
indicates the time ct and indices 1 2 3
indicates the space directions xyz.
With these spac-time summation indices,
it's very common to use the notation of
raising and lowering indices using the
manovsky metric ADA. For example, we can
take the ADA summed with a derivative
with a lowered index and replace it with
a derivative with a raised index. This
allows us to write the Klein Gordon
equation like this.
So now that we have some background with
the Klein Gordon equation, let's
actually solve it. This is the Klein
Gordon equation with three dimensions of
space and one dimension of time, also
called 3 + 1 spacetime. And its solution
is a little more complicated. So to
simplify things, we'll get rid of the y
and zed directions and just look at the
Klein Gordon equation with one dimension
of space and one dimension of time,
which is the 1 + 1 space-time version.
So we're only going to look at the time
and x terms and ignore the y and zed
terms.
The solutions to this Klein Gordon
equation are given by cosine waves where
omega is the wave's angular frequency in
time and K is the wave's angular
frequency in space, also called the
angular wave number. You might find it a
bit weird how I'm dividing the frequency
by C and then multiplying time by C
since these factors would just cancel
out. But these extra factors of C ensure
both time and space have units of meters
and ensure that frequency and wave
number both have units of one over
meters. If you like, you can cancel
these C's or use natural units and set C
equal to one. But I'm going to leave
these factors of C in
to see why this cosine solution works.
Let's look at the Klein Gordon equation
term by term. To take the derivative
with respect to ct, we treat ct as a
single variable in the formula.
Equivalently, we can treat this as 1 / c
* a time derivative. If you want,
so the derivative of cosine is negative
sign. And by chain rule, we get a factor
of omega / c. If we take the derivative
again, s becomes cosine and we get
another factor of omega / c by chain
rule. So for our cosine solution we see
that phi and the second derivative of
phi with respect to time are
proportional where the proportionality
constant is the negative frequency
squared.
If we look at the x derivative term we
see that we get something similar except
the proportionality constant is the
negative wave number squared instead.
So looking at the Klein Gordon equation
and assuming our cosine solution, we can
replace the second time derivative with
negative frequency squared and replace
the second x derivative with negative
wave number squared.
Finally, we can also combine these terms
together and divide both sides by the
field phi.
In the end, we get this relationship
here between mass, frequency, and wave
number. This is called the dispersion
relation and I'll explain why in a
moment.
So to solve the Klein Gordon equation,
we can pick any cosine wave with any
frequency or wave number as long as they
obey this dispersion relation.
It's also worth noting that if we take
this basic cosine solution and include a
scale factor a and a phase factor theta,
this is still a solution to the Klein
Gordon equation because the scale and
phase factors don't impact the
differential equation.
You might also recall the cosine angle
sum identity. This allows us to split
the cosine into a sum of a term with
cosiness and a term with ss. And we can
rewrite the scale factor a times the
trig functions of theta as new scaling
constants.
So giving the cosine wave a phase factor
is the same thing as writing a sum of a
cosine wave and a sine wave.
Another way to rewrite the basic cosine
solution is using Oilers's formula.
Taking the real part of a complex
exponential is the same thing as a
cosine wave. We can also include the
complex exponential of the phase factor
theta into the real scale factor a to
give us a new complex scale factor.
So we can use the real part of this
solution for real fields or we can use
the entire complex wave if the field is
complex.
Now, one last thing to note about the
Klein Gordon equation is that it's
linear. This means that if we have a
wave fi 1 and another wave fi 2, which
both solve the Klein Gordon equation,
then their sum fi 1 + 52 is also a
solution to the Klein Gordon equation.
This is easily checked as seen here.
This means that we can add an infinite
number of different wave solutions
together to get another solution.
We can even do an infinite continuous
sum over basic cosine solutions by doing
an integral over the wave number K since
K is a continuous variable.
It's also worth noting that in the most
general case both cosine and sine waves
solve the equation and we can
alternatively write the solutions using
complex exponentials if we want.
So we know for the 1D Klein Gordon
equation the basis solutions are
sinosoidal waves that obey this
dispersion relation. And since the Klein
Gordon equation is linear, we can add
any number of these basic syosoidal
solutions together to get a new
solution.
Generalizing to the three spaced
dimensional version of the Klein Gordon
equation is easy. We just use the same
basic cosine solution, but using x, y,
and zed terms where each of x, y, and
zed has its own wave number.
If we define omega over c as the time
component of the wave number, these four
k components can be assembled into a
four vector called the wave number four
vector.
And we can rewrite the cosine argument
as a simple summation.
We call these basic solutions plain wave
solutions
because the components of the wave
number vector indicate the orientation
of planes in the wave.
Now, since the Klein Gordon equation has
wavelike solutions, it's worth asking
what speed these waves travel at. One
basic way to find the wave speed is to
take the ratio of the angular frequency
omega and the angular wave number K.
This ratio has the expected units of
velocity.
But we can also visualize the wave speed
on a space-time diagram.
Frequency indicates how many wave peaks
we see in a given unit of time at a
constant position. And wave number
indicates how many wave peaks we see in
a given unit of space at a constant
time.
If we know what these densities are, we
can draw the world lines of the peaks of
the wave on the space-time diagram. And
the slopes of these wave peak world
lines will tell us how fast the wave is
traveling.
So let's compute this ratio omega over K
for our Klein Gordon solutions.
To do this, let's start with our
dispersion relation for the Klein Gordon
equation. So we'll bring the wave number
term to the other side, changing its
sign. Then we'll divide both sides by K^
2 and then multiply both sides by C^ 2.
Now to get our desired ratio omega over
k, we just take the square root of both
sides and we get this for the wave
velocity.
Now this result is actually a bit
concerning. If we were dealing with a
massless field where m equals 0, then
the wave speed would be the speed of
light c, which is fine. But if the field
has a nonzero mass, then the speed of
the wave is actually greater than the
speed of light c. since this term under
the square root sign is always greater
than one. So you might think this means
we've broken the rules of special
relativity.
However, it turns out this result is
actually fine if we understand the
difference between the phase velocity of
a wave and the group velocity of a wave.
As you can see here, this traveling wave
has an outer envelope which is traveling
more slowly and inner wave peaks that
are traveling more quickly.
The slower outer envelope is what is
actually capable of transmitting
information. So if we want to obey the
laws of special relativity and not send
information faster than light, this
envelope's group velocity must be less
than or equal to the speed of light C.
The fast inner wave peaks are not
capable of transmitting information. So
it's actually fine if the phase velocity
of these peaks is faster than light.
The omega over k ratio we calculated
before is the phase velocity. So it's
fine that this is faster than light
because this will not transmit
information.
If you think about it, a single
traveling cosine wave that looks the
same everywhere in time and space cannot
be used to transmit any information.
Now what about the group velocity?
Well, let's consider a Klein Gordon
solution that is made of a sum of two
basic cosine waves with frequencies and
wave numbers labeled 1 and two.
Now, if we take the cosine angle sum
trig identity and the cosine angle
difference trig identity and add them
together, we see that a sum of two
cosine waves can actually be rewritten
as the product of two cosine waves. We
can also switch some of the variables
around to get this easier to understand
formula here.
So if we have our two Klein Gordon waves
summed together here, we can use this
new trig identity to rewrite it as a
product of two cosine waves. One where
the frequencies and wave numbers are
added and one where the frequencies and
wave numbers are subtracted.
The cosine with the addition signs
represents the inner waves that travel
with the wave's phase velocity.
And the cosine with the minus signs
represents the outer wave envelope that
travels with the wave's group velocity.
So the group velocity would just be the
omega over k ratio for this outer cosine
wave which is omega 1 - omega 2 over k1
- k2.
We can also write this as delta omega
over delta k.
Now here we had a sum of just two cosine
waves. But if instead we had a
continuous spectrum of different cosine
waves with different frequencies and
wave numbers, this difference formula
for the group velocity would become a
derivative.
So this derivative is what gives us the
equation for the group velocity of the
wave envelope.
Let's return to our Klein Gordon
dispersion relation from before. If we
isolate omega squared and then take the
square root, we can then take the
derivative of both sides with respect to
K to calculate the group velocity.
Treating the square root as a 1/2
exponent, we can use power rule to
decrease the exponent by one and put a
factor of 1/2 in front and then use
chain rule to get an extra factor of the
derivative of k^ 2 which is 2 k.
The 1/2 and 2 cancel and the - 1/2
exponent gives us a square root in the
denominator. So this is the group
velocity formula.
For a massless field with m equals z,
the group velocity simply becomes c. But
for a massive field, this term in the
denominator is always going to be bigger
than k since m is positive. Which means
that the group velocity is always going
to be less than the speed of light.
So this shows us that the speed of
information contained in the wave cannot
exceed the speed of light. So the Klein
Gordon field obeys the laws of special
relativity.
Now I'll finally talk about why this
relation is called the dispersion
relation. If we imagine a set of basic
cosine solutions with different
frequencies and wave numbers, then each
basic wave will travel at a different
phase velocity depending on the value of
its wave number K. Since the mass m is
constant for the whole field,
we can see that when k is very large,
the phase velocity will be about the
speed of light. But when k gets smaller
and smaller, the phase velocity will get
bigger and bigger. So this means that
our collection of basic cosine waves
will all travel at different speeds. So
any envelope shape that they have when
the wave starts traveling will gradually
start to deform or disperse as the wave
travels along. And this is why we call
this the dispersion relation.
However, in the special case of massless
fields where m equals 0, the phase
velocity for every basic cosine wave is
always the speed of light c regardless
of what the wave number is.
This means that the wave envelope in
massless fields will not disperse and
will maintain its shape forever.
Now there's one last thing I want to
talk about which is the complex version
of the Klein Gordon field and how it
relates to antimatter.
So we've already seen the real version
of the Klein Gordon Lrangeian where the
function fi outputs a real number and
when we put this through the oiler
lrange equation we get the Klein Gordon
equation
but now let's consider the complex Klein
Gordon Lrangeian where phi outputs a
complex number in this lrgonian instead
of squaring the terms we take the
squared magnitude of the terms.
This means each term in the sum involves
an expression times its complex
conjugate.
For the derivative terms, since the
variables we are taking derivatives with
respect to are real, they are not
affected by the complex conjugate. So
the star can just be moved to fi.
Now it's worth noting that one complex
field can be viewed as two real fields
since the complex fi has both a real
part and an imaginary part.
However, when dealing with the field
equations, it's more useful to consider
phi and its complex conjugate phi star
as the main field variables instead.
So with this complex lrangeian, if we
put it through the oiler lrange equation
varying with respect to phi, we get the
klein gordon equation for fi star. But
we can also put this lrangeian through
the oiler lrange equation varying for fi
star and we get the klein gordon
equation for fi. So we actually get two
klein gordon equations here.
Also these overall factors of 1/2 don't
impact the physics. So we typically
remove them from the lrangeian.
So here phi represents matter particles
and phi star represents the
corresponding antimatter particles with
opposite charge.
So scalar matter and antimatter
particles can sort of be viewed as
different types of excitations in the
same scalar complex field related by the
complex conjugate.
So if the standard matter excitation is
a complex exponential with a positive
sign, then the corresponding antimatter
excitation is a complex exponential with
a negative sign. These two excitations
have the same real part but opposite
signed imaginary parts.
Now to understand electric charge we'll
look at this lrangeian's u1 symmetry
where u1 is the group of all 1x1
unititary matrices which is just the set
of complex numbers with magnitude 1. If
we transform phi by multiplying it by a
complex phase, then phi star will
transform with the same complex phase
but in the opposite direction since the
complex conjugate will change the sign
of the i in the exponent.
If we take our lrronian and apply this
u1 phase transformation to the field
phi, all of these complex phases do not
depend on the space-time variables. So
we can pull them in and out of the
space-time derivatives.
This means that every positive phase
will get cancelled by a corresponding
negative phase. So the overall arrange
is left unchanged by this U1 phase
transformation.
Now a theorem called nottor's theorem
tells us that every continuous symmetry
in a lronian will always result in a
conserved quantity. We can see this
conserved quantity if we look at the
Klein Gordon equations for fi and phi
star.
We'll multiply the fi equation on the
left by fi star and multiply the phi
star equation on the left by phi. Now
let's subtract the equations which will
cancel the mass terms but leave the
derivative terms.
Now I'll add and subtract this term with
derivatives of phi and phi star. These
first two terms have a lower mu
derivative on the left on the first term
and on the right in the second term. So
they can be grouped together using
product rule in reverse. The same is
true for grouping the third and fourth
terms.
Overall we get this equation here
equaling zero.
We can consider this formula here in the
brackets to be a current for vector J
and this obeys a continuity equation.
This basically means there's a charge
density which is the time component of
J. And the only way this charge density
can change over time is if there's a
convergence or divergence of some
current at a given point. This is the
electric charge current. And since it
obeys the continuity equation, this
means that total electric charge is
conserved over time.
Now I will point out that this four
vector current we've defined here is
purely imaginary.
We can see this by taking the complex
conjugate of the formula then
distributing the star to all the terms
inside and seeing that we get the
negative of the original four vector.
Since the complex conjugate equals the
negative this means that J is purely
imaginary.
Because of this, we usually define J by
multiplying this formula by the complex
I to make the result purely real.
Now, everything we've said so far is
true in classical field theory. But
let's jump ahead and take a quick look
at quantum field theory where the field
functions become quantum operators.
This will lead us to creation and
annihilation operators for both matter
and antimatter particles.
There are also number operators for
counting the number of matter and
antimatter particles with a given wave
number K.
There is also an electric charge
operator Q which is related to the
difference in the number of matter and
antimatter particles and this is
conserved over time.
The Higs field related to the famous
Higs Bzon is actually a pair of complex
scalar fields in its original form and
its free behavior ignoring interactions
is described by the complex Klein Gordon
field.
So let's sum up everything we've learned
about the Klein Gordon equation in this
video.
We learned that the Klein Gordon Lronian
is inspired by an infinite field of
masses on springs connected with rubber
bands. And each term in the Klein Gordon
lrangeian represents either kinetic
energy or potential energy in this
field. When we put this lrangeian
through the oiler lrangege equations, we
get the Klein Gordon equation which
describes how the field fi evolves over
time. This is the 1 + 1 space-time
version of the Klein Gordon equation.
But we can also write down the 3 + 1
spac-time version with XY Z variables.
The basic solutions to the Klein Gordon
equation are sinosoidal waves which can
be written in many different ways.
And since the Klein Gordon equation is
linear, any sum of scaled sinosoid
solutions will give another valid
solution.
We also learned about the difference
between the phase velocity and group
velocity of Klein Gordon solutions.
It is only the group velocity that is
capable of transmitting information. So
it is limited by the speed of light.
However, the phase velocity does not
have this limit.
Finally, we learned about the complex
Klein Gordon field which gives both
matter and antimatter solutions.
And we learned that the U1 symmetry of
this lronian leads to a conserved
current which is the electric current
for vector. And this obeys a continuity
equation.
In the next video, we're going to look
at the procrangeian
which describes vector fields.